<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-03-25T12:36:33-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Solim LeGris</title><subtitle>personal webpage</subtitle><entry><title type="html">An Aspiring Scientist’s Thoughts on Becoming One</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/anglais/2022/03/24/aspiring-scientist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Aspiring Scientist’s Thoughts on Becoming One" /><published>2022-03-24T12:45:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-03-24T12:45:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/anglais/2022/03/24/aspiring-scientist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/anglais/2022/03/24/aspiring-scientist.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-start-of-a-journey&quot;&gt;The start of a journey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applying to graduate school was stressful and it required a lot of careful thinking about potential advisors, research interests and places to live among many things. I recently was offered a position as a PhD student in two very good universities with researchers at the top of their fields. I was extremely excited and euphoric both times I read the admission offer emails. I think that like many other people who have tended to be on the far end in terms of intellectual curiosity (aka nerdy-ness) since a young age, entering a world-class institution to be trained for high level research is a dream come true. And on top of that you get paid to do it. Not very much but still, you can focus 100% of your time on doing something you’re passionate about!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on my own experiences, what I know, what I want to know and especially what I hope to be researching as a PhD student has been on my mind lately. It certainly can get terrifying at times. Regardless of the fact that I have been found to be worthy of a position as a PhD student and that I came off as qualified, it doesn’t always feel like that. It’s often a mixed feeling of “I can do this!” but also “Can I really?”. So being the person that I am, I came up with a loose plan for the next few months before I embark on my PhD journey. The idea is to work on skills that from my (naive) perspective I think will be useful as a researcher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-research-to-me&quot;&gt;What is research to me?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I see it, good research is often about &lt;em&gt;finding a mapping from solutions of fully or partially solved problems to new/unsolved problems&lt;/em&gt;. In the context of computational cognitive science, this can be using techniques developed in a totally different context and adapting them to the human intelligence/cognition problem. For example, during my undergraduate, I was interested in a specific cognitive phenomenon called categorical perception and I used a deep neural network to model &lt;em&gt;functionally&lt;/em&gt; what might be happening in learning systems that have some of the properties of neural networks like the fact that they learn distributed representations. Deep neural networks were not developed as models of specific phenomena in brains or minds (although loosely inspired by them), they were developed as a powerful statistical learning tool that set a new paradigm in artificial intelligence research. I don’t really believe in the 100% novel ideas. I just don’t think human intelligence works that way. Even totally groundbreaking ideas have some &lt;em&gt;grounding&lt;/em&gt; in other ideas. There’s a reason we often use the metaphor “standing on the shoulders of giants”. We spin up new things by reusing old things we know in novel ways. The novelty of an idea is probably a function of the distance between the ideas that the analogies and mappings used to come up with a solution connect. If this is true, then doing research is in part feeding your intellectual curiosity, letting it ride wild and asking a lot of questions. A lot of what you do  will inevitably fail but that’s just part of doing science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-should-i-feed-my-intellectual-curiosity&quot;&gt;How should I feed my intellectual curiosity?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The space of answers to this question is like &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;vast&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Nonetheless, there are some constraints I can think of that would be helpful. It can be hard to not go in all directions and end up feeling like you’re still in square zero. For an aspiring computational cognitive scientist, getting into the habit of reading research papers is one way of feeding your intellectual curiosity. It’s hard to know what to read at times but I like to build my way up from the ground by looking for fundamental problems in the field. There is also a wealth of resources out there put together by people who have already started this journey (some of which I’ll link below). Just pick one and stick with it! I think one of the more important things is to engage deeply with what you’re reading: summarize it, be critical, compare it to other things you’ve read, ask questions about the solutions presented, etc. Here are some of the questions I’ve come up with to ask about any research paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the contribution of this paper and the solution presented?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are some of the problems with this solution?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is this solution unique?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How would I improve this solution?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the design of the study valid? Does it really measure what it intends to measure?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of feeding your intellectual curiosity is finding textbooks, web-books or just books pertaining to your field of research that you can go through end-to-end or select chapters from to go through. The advantage with those is that someone has already thought about what they think is important for the specific topic they wrote a book about and it can be an invaluable resource to point you towards other relevant literature to read as well. Not only that, they often contain questions that make you think about what you’ve read or implement/write up solutions to problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For computational cognitive science, being deeply familiar with technical tools is definitely important. I like to implement algorithms from scratch using a minimal amount of libraries in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/code&gt;. I want to emphasize the “from scratch” aspect because it’s too easy these days to just copy/paste code from the Internet without understanding what it’s doing! I’ve found over the years that implementing an algorithm is one of the best ways to understand how a model works. It forces you to really think about how all the equations come together, why they work and what they do. Implementing an algorithm is also in a way explaining a model, but in a computer language. You have to understand it or else your computer won’t behave as intended! It also tangentially makes you a better programmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last thing I’d like to mention is that I don’t think feeding your intellectual curiosity should be just about engaging with the literature in your specific field of research. As I’ve mentioned before, good ideas can come from surprising places. Thinking about things outside of your field of research can be fruitful too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;letting-your-mind-go-wild&quot;&gt;Letting your mind go wild&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me letting the mind go wild is about taking a break, focusing on my hobbies for a little, working out, playing games, socializing, etc. Coming back to a problem with a fresh mind can definitely help you solve it and some research supports this idea. One of the more fruitful ways of letting your mind go wild is probably writing. Putting into writing your thoughts about a specific topic lets your mind loose but in the end you come out with a more structured way of thinking about that topic. It also has the tendency to allow you to identify gaps in your understanding. I think the blog style fits my needs best since it entails sharing my thoughts publicly which makes me more mindful about how clearly I am writing, how structured my thoughts are and so on without being overly formal (and this holds even if you have no actual or substantial audience).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is definitely not an exhaustive list of how to improve or acquire skills that will be useful for graduate school and scientific endeavours in general. One of the things I’m really curious about in writing this is how my perspective will shift in the next few years, coming back here to read a young, excited and potentially naive aspiring researcher’s thoughts on science and how to become better at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cogscikid.com/ML-Brain-Resources/brain&quot;&gt;ML-Brain-Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mlcompendium.gitbook.io/machine-and-deep-learning-compendium/&quot;&gt;Machine and Deep Learning Compendium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/YuzheSHI/awesome-agi-cocosci&quot;&gt;Awesome AGI and CoCoSci&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AMAI-GmbH/AI-Expert-Roadmap&quot;&gt;AI Expert Roadmap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Solim LeGris</name></author><category term="anglais" /><summary type="html">The start of a journey Applying to graduate school was stressful and it required a lot of careful thinking about potential advisors, research interests and places to live among many things. I recently was offered a position as a PhD student in two very good universities with researchers at the top of their fields. I was extremely excited and euphoric both times I read the admission offer emails. I think that like many other people who have tended to be on the far end in terms of intellectual curiosity (aka nerdy-ness) since a young age, entering a world-class institution to be trained for high level research is a dream come true. And on top of that you get paid to do it. Not very much but still, you can focus 100% of your time on doing something you’re passionate about!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">La science paradigmatique</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/francais/2020/12/28/science-paradigmatique.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="La science paradigmatique" /><published>2020-12-28T12:20:26-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-28T12:20:26-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/francais/2020/12/28/science-paradigmatique</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/francais/2020/12/28/science-paradigmatique.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Une science qui hésite à oublier ses fondateurs est condamnée&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; - Alfred North Whitehead&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La science est communément perçue comme étant une accumulation linéaire de connaissances obtenues à l’aide d’une application rigoureuse de la méthode scientifique et d’une ouverture d’esprit aux nouvelles idées. Rigueur, rationalité, connaissance mais aussi créativité, génie de l’individu, révolutions et autres caractérisations communes des sciences portent à confusion car elles omettent des contextes et des dynamiques socio-historiques. Ces conceptions ne sont pas représentatives de la science et de son histoire comme le démontre Thomas Kuhn dans son &lt;em&gt;The Function of Dogma in Scientific Research&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Pour Kuhn, il y a un fondement vital de la pratique scientifique et contraire aux intuitions d’historiens des sciences le précédant dont la conception des sciences ne tenait pas compte d’une cohérence interne, d’une sociologie, en quelque sorte, de la pratique et de l’épistémologie scientifique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Par une étude approfondie de l’histoire des sciences, Kuhn en est venu à caractériser ce qu’il appelle la science normale qui est « basée sur le paradigme ». Il remarque que « le dogmatisme de la science mature » a comme conséquence une acceptation consensuelle dans la communauté scientifique « d’une façon particulière de voir le monde et d’y pratiquer la science ». D’autant plus, le paradigme scientifique d’une discipline donnée est un « accomplissement fondamental […] accepté [du groupe] dans le sens où il est reçu par un groupe dans lequel les membres ne tentent pas de le rivaliser ou d’en créer une alternative ». Cet engagement quasi-dogmatique de la communauté scientifique envers leur paradigme est essentiel au progrès scientifique selon Kuhn. Grâce à celui-ci, « la science [est] la plus systématiquement révolutionnaire de toutes les activités humaines ».&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La science normale n’a donc pas comme but de générer des nouvelles théories qui renverseront les précédentes : c’est en fait un processus de raffinement qui a pour but de solidifier ce qui est connu par des expériences scientifiques dont la problématique ainsi que les interprétations acceptables sont déterminées par le paradigme même. Le paradigme d’une science est en conséquence le fondement intellectuel enseigné aux étudiants de la science pour leur permettre de générer, à partir de celui-ci, des nouvelles questions de recherche qui seront à leurs tour approchées et évaluées par une méthodologie définie par la structure du paradigme et les postulats de la théorie dominante d’une époque. Puisque « de nouvelles théories ne sont pas inventées pour tenir compte d’observations qui n’avaient pas été ordonnées auparavant par la théorie [du paradigme] », la majorité des données qui sont acceptées et publiées se conforment au schème général d’une discipline quelconque. C’est seulement lorsque les scientifiques ne parviennent plus à faire conformer leurs résultats à la théorie, et ce de façon répétée, que ce que Kuhn appelle une « crise » émerge au sein de la communauté scientifique. Ces anomalies irrésolues indiquent potentiellement un changement éminent de paradigme résultant en une révolution scientifique, une transition vers un nouveau paradigme incompatible avec l’ancien.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;À premier abord, l’analyse de Kuhn est décontenançante. Elle cause nécessairement un désillusionnement chez le profane et même chez le scientifique face à la nature du fonctionnement historique, sociologique et épistémologique de la science. Cette dernière vue comme une accumulation linéaire serait en soi une contradiction : il n’y aurait de scientifique que ce qui est actuel, ce qui assurément n’a aucun sens. La loi universelle de la gravitation de Newton n’est pas moins scientifique que la relativité générale qui explique mieux les trajectoires de corps célestes. La différence majeure est que les nouvelles théories sont considérées comme fondamentales par la communauté scientifique dans deux contextes socio-historiques et épistémologiques non seulement différents mais aussi incompatibles. Les théories désuètes sont rejetées parce qu’il y a des changements de paradigmes, incompatibles les uns avec les autres, et non pas parce qu’elles n’étaient pas conformes à la pensée et à la méthode scientifique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nous pouvons considérer l’endoctrinement scientifique comme une forme d’internalisation de biais épistémologiques propres à une époque, une discipline et un contexte paradigmatique. Les biais épistémologiques sont assimilés comme structure de la pensée qui permet de générer, préciser et perfectionner les ramifications théoriques du paradigme actuel. Cet endoctrinement est nécéssaire, si nous nous fions à l’analyse de Kuhn, pour le progrès scientifique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dans le balado &lt;em&gt;How to Think About Science: Lorraine Daston&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Daston nous présente sa réflexion approfondie et inspirée par les idées de Kuhn sur le rôle de l’émerveillement et de la curiosité à travers l’histoire Occidentale ainsi que les différentes métamorphoses de l’objectivité de siècle en siècle. Selon elle, « différentes conceptions de l’objectivité répondent à différentes craintes quant à la façon dont la pensée peut être induite en erreur » et je crois que les biais épistémologiques inculqués par l’éducation scientifique et paradigmatique sont précisément des réponses à ces craintes. Par exemple, Daston décrit la forme dominante d’objectivité du 19e siècle, l’objectivité mécanique, comme une peur du moi psychanalytique, le substrat inconscient d’un individu, qui est perçu comme une menace à la connaissance scientifique. Il y a donc, à cette époque, une tentative très forte de diviser le monde en sujets et objets, où la volonté doit dominer sur les pulsions intérieures et l’expérience subjective. De façon similaire aux métamorphoses de l’objectivité et des différentes formes de rationalités qui évoluent historiquement, les biais paradigmatiques, eux aussi, subissent des métamorphoses. Certes, l’analyse de Kuhn s’applique au sens large à la communauté scientifique, mais il traite aussi dans son ouvrage indirectement de l’individu qui acquiert par sa formation ces biais. Le scientifique ne peut plus être considéré comme un explorateur de l’inconnu au sens large, comme l’image mystique et populaire du scientifique nous le présente, puisque son internalisation de la structure de la pensée scientifique de son époque agit comme guide dans la recherche qu’il mène.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cette nouvelle conception du scientifique nous amène à revoir celle du scientifique poussé par la curiosité, défiant sans cesse les théories de son époque ou faisant des découvertes spectaculaires. Il ne faut pas pour autant dorénavant penser le scientifique comme un être purement dogmatique. Il y a, je crois, place pour l’émerveillement, la curiosité, la rebellion et le spectaculaire. L’esprit du scientifique et de sa communauté demeure un lieu fertile mais on y retrouve une certaine tension, une dialectique en quelque sorte entre le dogmatisme scientifique et la recherche de nouveauté. Le scientifique se retrouve à la fois contraint par les biais épistémologiques de son paradigme qui sont renforcés par sa communauté ainsi que son éducation et poussé par un besoin inhérent et terriblement humain de patauger dans des eaux inconnues. Cette tension entre le chaos de l’inconnu et l’ordre de la structure de la recherche scientifique me semble être un état à l’équilibre fragile. Trop d’ordre, et la science deviendrait stagnante, trop de chaos, et celle-ci ne serait plus science mais plutôt une activité aléatoire et peu productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Whitehead, A. N. (1959). The aims of education. Daedalus, 88(1), 192-205. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Kuhn, T. S. (1963). The function of dogma in scientific research (pp. 347-369). na. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cayley, D., Kennedy, P. (Hosts). (2015, Feb. 11). How To Think About Science - Part 2. In &lt;em&gt;In How to Think About Science&lt;/em&gt;. CBC Ideas. https://www.cbc.ca/player/play/1479827155 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Solim LeGris</name></author><category term="francais" /><summary type="html">Une science qui hésite à oublier ses fondateurs est condamnée1 - Alfred North Whitehead Whitehead, A. N. (1959). The aims of education. Daedalus, 88(1), 192-205. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry></feed>